hey Arin how you doing good how are you
good
thanks um that good it's great we got uh
we got you on camera right now great so
it's great to see you uh happy holidays
how's all the kids getting ready for
everything yeah yeah um
both Heather and I have some travel
um from London yesterday she's got to
run to Saudi Arabia in a couple of days
and then I'm going to go to I'm going to
go to Austin tomorrow come back on uh
Thursday for a speech so it's been
busy well good busy and you've been
traveling a lot been traveling a lot uh
Seattle
Minneapolis New York
Cincinnati Los Angeles that was a big
one well let me introduce you to the
people who are watching this this is
John kyaku who's a former CIA agent who
was stationed in
Pakistan uh during um up and with the
CIA until 2005 or 2006 four four and uh
one of his uh greatest moments was
capturing Abu Abu Abu Zaba which was he
was number three uh on the terrorist
list under uh
Al-Qaeda and I may have time to ask you
a little bit about that and then in 2007
did an interview and gave information
about the CIA torture uh and
consequently was arrested and served uh
almost 3 years in jail and was released
earlier this year so he's a hero he also
has multiple degrees uh he speaks mult M
languages both uh Arabic and Greece
Greek and English he's traveled through
many of the countries in the Middle East
in Europe has served our country both in
uh Greece uh Pakistan um during the uh
Gulf War he was stationed uh or his his
job was managing the information uh with
uh Iraq so he's a wealth of information
we could talk to him for hours but uh
you know where I would like to start
John is where is your head right now
what are you thinking about what are you
seeing and paying attention to um as an
analyst and as a person working for the
institute for uh public
U studies policy studies um you know to
tell you the truth I'm I'm trying to get
away from the whole whistleblower
thing um that has I
think a finite life to it and I spent so
many years uh in government working on
the Middle East and on terrorism I mean
to tell you the truth I was one of the
government's leading experts on the
Middle East I have um Eastern studies I
I concentrated on Islamic theology I
speak the language I know the the
religion um and I I'd like to get back
into U Middle Eastern um
analysis uh so with with the Advent of
Isis
and and other problems frankly that
we're having in the region whether it's
Syria and Iraq or Libya or Iran I'd like
to I'd like to focus more than I have
over the past several years on the
Middle East great because that's where I
wanted to go in the interview so I'll
just get right there um we have a
president that has indicted more
whistleblowers than anyone in the
history of the United States most people
don't know that uh we're B he's bombing
uh seven countries he's uh pretty much
perfected the use of drones every week
and we've communicated over the past
couple of weeks we're seeing a new turn
of event in the Middle East um I
contacted you a couple weeks ago when
turkey took down the plane in uh the
Russian uh jet in uh right before
Thanksgiving a lot of information has
come out since then as to what might
beis of selling oil both to Assad and to
Turkey so could you pull pull away uh
some of the layers of the onion here and
tell us what what do you think's
happening in the yeah sure but first I
think there are no good guys in this in
this entire uh situation um what what
Isis is doing Visa V oil sales is really
very typical of what extremist groups
have done um over the past 15 or 20
years
if they control any territory they
exploit the natural resources in that
territory or not even natural but the
resources in that territory or they
conduct highlevel kidnappings it's it's
really quite a lucrative way um of uh of
financing your movement so one of the
things that Isis has done uh really from
the get-go is once they began capturing
uh parts of Northern Iraq
and oil they kept those oil facilities
running so that they could
surreptitiously um ship the oil across
the border into turkey and then from
Turkey onto the gray Market uh the
Iraqis used to do this during the
sanctions regime between 1991 and and
2003 Isis knew that it worked uh Iraqi
Military Officers who now largely make
up isis's leadership already had the
relationship with um with Turks who on
the other side of the Border who
could take the oil and so this is really
the main way in which Isis um earns its
money there are other groups though
al-Qaeda in um the Islamic mreb for
example that's active in North Africa
and and the Sahel and they tend to favor
uh kidnapping because there is no no oil
um in the Sahel or there's very very
little oil in the Sahel so what they'll
do is kidnap it Italians or French or
belgians or South Africans knowing full
well that their governments will pay a
ransom very quietly and then that's how
they raise their money so this is really
nothing new and the reason why these
groups are doing it is because it's so
successful but you said there are no
good guys in any of this uh turkey is a
NATO Nation the United States is selling
weapons to Turkey the United States is
selling weapons to Saudi Arabia Saudi
Arabia is financing al-nusra possibly
Isis uh do you think that Isis is
somehow doing some of the dirty work for
any of our allies or the United States
in order to top bu
Assad I I do I do the the Turks really
have no inherent uh beef with Isis Isis
hasn't really directly attacked uh
turkey as as a country or the
Turks um but they have a common enemy in
the Kurds and so you know the United
States begged turkey to to get involved
in this fight and to allow us to use
inic air base and the Turks you know
played hard to get for a little while
and then announced that they would
indeed come in on the side of the allies
and
immedi Kurdish positions along the
border so really turkey's not doing much
of anything to help uh the
Allies Isis the Turks actually like the
status quo where they're making money
from the trans shipment of the oil and
they have Western permission to bomb uh
the Kurds as well well you have no love
loss for the CIA nor do you for
President Obama so what involvement do
you think that they have in in Syria and
Iraq I think CIA involvement in Syria
has been a absolute debacle uh they
created this this ridiculous
organization called the free Syrian Army
spent hundreds and hundreds of millions
of dollars to train almost no body and
then announced at the very end that it
was an utter failure and it just fell
apart with no plan to do anything beyond
that um really the White House's only
plan is to encourage our so-called
allies involved and when I say so-called
I mean allies like you pointed out Saudi
Arabia that frankly um uh funds Isis
Andra uh maybe not the Saudi government
but CER certainly wealthy Saudis uh
businessmen and even Royal family
members we've seen this for for decades
where Saudis were were financing Afghan
Arabs during the Soviet uh occupation of
Afghanistan and even during uh the US's
war with uh Al-Qaeda and the Taliban we
see Saudi Nationals funding um al-Qaeda
in the Islamic mreb they're funding
al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula this
is an ongoing thing with the Saudis and
it's something that that neither the
White House nor the CIA um have ever
really addressed with the Saudi
government you broke up but you said the
United States role is to encourage is
that the word you used allies to to
encourage our Arab allies to do
something but we're encouraging the
wrong Arabs we're encouraging the Saudis
in fact the Saudis are on the wrong side
of this issue there's a lot of Scholars
that are writing that the United States
might be having an ulterior motive
that's not a very uh healthy one for our
uh our best interests in the Middle East
are you seeing any of that do you think
that there's a a desire to have uh Syria
destabilized for oil interests with the
the the buying between the two pipeline
negotiations that have been going on for
the past year I I don't think we're that
smart uh to be perfectly honest with you
I think that um that we've got a stupid
policy and it's stupid because it's
stupid not because there's an ulterior
motive um we don't learn from our
mistakes historically and anytime
there's trouble in the Middle East our
knee-jerk reaction is to send troops um
if if we decide we don't like somebody
we decide to overthrow that person
whether or not there's a plan for a
transition to a peaceful government
afterwards look at Saddam Hussein we
provided Saddam Hussein with top secret
intelligence during his War uh with Iran
now this was a war of Iraqi aggression
against Iran but we provided the Iraqis
with intelligence to keep that War uh
going when we decided we didn't like
Saddam Hussein anymore we decided to
overthrow him so we attack Iraq we
overthrow Saddam Hussein who was the
only bull workk in the in the region
against uh Iranian
expansionism and now we've got a a Shia
government in Iraq that is friendly with
the Iranians and that is hostile to many
of the the Region's uh Sunni U uh
kingdoms and and Emirates and we can't
figure out why the Iranians feel
empowered
well you say you we didn't like um
Saddam it was also he was nationalizing
the oil and so was well no then the oil
had been nationalized many years earlier
the the the oil had been um nationalized
by President Bacher after the 68
Revolution so it wasn't Saddam
nationalizing Iraqi oil it was already
nationalized when he was vice president
got it okay so it was just merely we
didn't like what he he was doing and so
we went in there and what he was doing
at the time was he uh there was a u a
conflict with Kuwait and there's
discrepancy as to whether or not um
Kuwait was starting to drill uh cross
borders into Iraq and whether or not
Kuwait uh provoked
Assad I mean Sadam yeah well I I think
that there really wasn't
a any confusion about whether or not the
Iraqis were slant drilling I mean the
quades were slant drilling they were
slant drilling U and they were they were
frankly stealing Iraqi oil but they had
been doing that many years and the
Iraqis knew that they were doing it I
mean I'm not I'm not trying to I'm not
trying to paint a revisionist picture of
Saddam Hussein this was a very bad man
this guy was a was a he committed
genocide um and there were some some
just human rights Horrors that were
committed
by's command in in Kuwait but with that
said
strategically over a long term it the
United States better to allow a
contained Saddam Hussein to remain in
power in Iraq then it would have been to
overthrow him and to allow to exert
influence in the country right what I'm
trying to get to without uh trying to
give uh take up too much of your time is
that since Kosovo the United States has
started to go into foreign countries
with the we'll say under the offices of
humanitarian interests and it's picking
and choosing which countries to go into
obviously we're not trying to help Yemen
uh with thousands of people being killed
by Saudi Arabia in in uh in Yemen uh
we're not in certain countries in Africa
so all of a sudden in the last 6 months
the rhetoric is built up very high on
why we're in s in Syria and it's become
increasingly more apparent that we're
there to get Assad out of power because
we and what's being said and Senate
hearings as of last week is because
Assad is a bad guy he's killing people
obviously there is a lot of wrongs going
on Assad Isis those type of things
however what what is not clear to me and
other people is why would we try to
bring troops into Syria when we don't
have authorization to bring troops into
Syria when what looks apparent is we're
not necessarily going after Isis you
know Isis is in seven countries we're
only bombing two an example like uh um
um what's the the the city in in Syria
raqqa in raqqa it's a city of 20,000
people you're an analyst there's 2,000
Isis fighters in raqqa and and four
countries are bombing the heck out of
raqqa well there that just doesn't make
sense to somebody like me because you
can only bomb so many targets before
you've exhausted everything that you
could be doing so what's really
happening on the ground in Syria and
Iraq are we really trying to degrade and
Destroy Isis or is this just something
we're telling the American people so
they feel like we're trying to do
something about it and tomorrow night's
Republican debate is going to work we
should put troops on the ground we
should have a safe Zone and all these
things that aren't going to
work right you know when you look at the
Genesis of of the problem with Isis
uh cre because of American policy
failures Isis was created in in an
American Military prison in Iraq in
2005 when abubakr Al baghdaddy uh and um
and friends and cohorts formerly of the
Iraqi Army together and decided that
they would launch a Sunni
um military and opposition group to
fight the the Shia government in Iraq um
the Iraqis weren't equipped to uh to
fight something like that uh especially
an organization militarily led by some
of Saddam Hussein's top former
generals and then they began capturing
thousands of pieces of American Military
Hardware uh and and they're that's what
they're using in this fight it's it's
American uh military hardware provided
by the United States to the Iraqi
government that was very easily captured
by ISIS um that's point one point two
you make a very important point in that
Isis is in seven countries we're only
bombing or we're only fighting them into
and we're we're bombing really I think
indiscriminately uh if press reports are
be to be believed uh but I but I'll go
one one better uh there are a lot of
countries in the world
despotic uh leaders there are a lot of
countries in the world where governments
don't respect human rights we didn't
intervene in Rwanda for example uh we
didn't intervene in East
teamour I mean the there are there are
dozens of examples around the world
where if we really had this respect this
this this overarching respect for human
rights that we profess to have we should
have been intervening all over the place
but these other countries don't have oil
and these other countries aren't tied to
the Middle East and tied
Tod East uh like Iraq and Syria are now
my final point would be
um this is a
situation
where there's no good outcome but you
can choose an outcome that's less
terrible than other outcomes and the
only outcome that's less terrible that
is available to us I think is that we
need to start talking to Bashar al-assad
and we need to start negotiating with
the Assad government and we need to
start working with the Russians to make
sure that there's a
viable government in Damascus that can
help all of us to work together to fight
Isis and I don't see that ever happening
while this administration's in
power the the thing that the news isn't
covering and that is not happening in
Congressional hearings with foreign
relations armed
services is with last week I watched
three and a half hours of asash Carter
present to John McCain what is shocking
to me is the lack of details that a
secretary of defense gives in any now
forget what is confidential information
or that I'm
just something doesn't smell right here
okay he is uh saying he has everything
that he needs being provided by the
president in order to De degrade and
Destroy Isis okay he has said on the one
hand that they've made advancements
where people uh where the chairman of
the joint Chief of Staff I believe has
said that they they aren't making
advances it doesn't matter all right
what what what doesn't smell right to me
is there's clearly not a military
strategy and there's really not a
political goal so what they're doing and
what has happened since Vietnam is they
just don't want to look like they're
weak they don't want to look like
they're backing off as you said it's a
very complicated issue and therefore
they have to look like they're
attempting to do something Meanwhile
we're in an election year and we have
Republicans stirring the pot by saying
we could do more the only other
opportunities that are presented in
order to do more is to put more troops
on the ground and the Delta between how
many we have and what they are uh crying
out for is 5 to 10,000 troops which
during 2007 there was 180,000 troops so
we know that's not going to make all
that much of a difference right right
okay the other thing they're now calling
out for is a safe Zone which is a buffer
between turkey and and Syria so that
Isis isn't getting arms back and forth
across the Turkish border correct and
but what they for the Syrian refugees to
not go into Europe and to be able to be
staying there and the military is saying
it take 30,000 troops in order to
protect a safe Zone and make that
operational so that yeah this is this is
it see all of our
plans
include the commitment of ground
troops so you can have people like ash
Carter or the president um promising
that there isn't going to be an uptick
in the number of of ground troops we
send and that's just not that's just not
possible there the only the only ideas
that the administration is floating at
least the ideas that are reaching the
the press include ground
troops so I I just don't see how the
administration expects to accomplish
anything um if there's no overall plan
and now you you've made another
important Point here too and that is
that there doesn't seem to be
coordination between the Allies well in
fact in the press the only coordination
that's even being discussed is um
coordination of what targets to
bomb
so what is the plan what is the strategy
I don't think I don't think there is a
strategy well the most recent twist to
this plot is the Iraqi prime minister is
stating that he does not want Alli
ground troops in this came out on Friday
does not want uh Allied ground troops in
Iraq so you have a a government that we
supported for 13 years saying that they
this is very similar to what has been
going on in Afghanistan they want
control they obviously cannot do
anything to stop
Isis in their country because they don't
have a very organized
military and so what that again if you
you know I'm going to bring it to two
points first this one that that kind of
says that the only place that we could
play War Games is in Syria and the
common denominator is people want Assad
out of power who are in the allies and
the reason well first of all we did that
to Gaddafi and that was a disaster it's
been chaos ever since right and now
they're trying to put a peace agreement
together and that's coming out in the
news today and over the weekend the
other issue is that why would we want
Assad out of power we're not do I I feel
as though we're not doing this because
we're the great humanitarian in police
state um we want am out of power because
there's oil interests that are going on
and I'm not sure I'm that I'm that
cynical because there there's really
very little oil in Syria I think we want
him out of power because he won't do
what we tell him to do I think that's
really what it is and what would we want
him to do whatever it is anything we say
I mean look look back over over the last
um 15 years or so or or even going back
earlier to 1991 when his father was in
power H as alas said uh Secretary of
State James Baker made a trip to
Damascus and said look we're going to
attack the Iraqis in Kuwait we're going
to push them out we have the Saudis we
have the the GCC we have the Egyptians
we have the Turks we want your help the
and the syrians helped us to push Iraq
out of Kuwait fast
forward I think President George W bush
went to Bashar al-assad after the death
of his father he became the the leader
of Syria and we said we're going to
attack Iraq we have your Arab allies we
have the jordanians we have the GCC we
have the Egyptians we have the Turks we
want your help he told us to go fly a
kite and on top of that he would not
allow us overflight clearance to
supply U the Kurds from Jordan so we had
to fly from Jordan across Israel out
over the Mediterranean loop around cross
turkey and come south from Turkey okay
it made the trip much longer it made the
trip very
dangerous well never gave him for that
so he wouldn't it stand to reason that
we would want to
install who Not only would do what we
told him to do but would end this
decades long close
relationship with the that makes sense
to me with a decade long relationship
with who the Iranians okay decades
multiple decades and Russia cuz Russia
has a naval base there the Russians have
been friendly with with the with the
syrians since the 1950s it's it's pretty
much Russia's only Ally in the Middle
East and I'm I'm not trying to be
cynical I'm I'm referencing many
different articles but you're probably
familiar with Pepe Escobar uh a
journalist who writes who's written an
article that this has to do with also
with the issue of the pipelines uh one
is benefiting would benefit the Soviet I
mean Russia and Iran and the other would
benefit Qatar Saudi AR Arabia and turkey
and and so um because you're run because
we don't have a lot of time I want to
jump to one other piece of the puzzle
Syria borders the north northern Israel
one of the buffers one of the areas
between that is the Golan Heights which
Israel took in
1967 took or however you could clarify
that for me because I'm I I I'm um I'm
not clear on that point but Israel has
been um very very
silent sure on the conflict in Syria
yeah very silent Israel is not known for
being quiet on anything right why is
this happening because the Israelis
support Assad it's very
simple the devil you know is better than
the devil you don't and the the Israelis
have had um a very long period of peace
with Syria it's a deao peace they're
still arguing about the Golan Heights I
mean not really but in public they are
but the syrians know that Assad is no
threat to them he never has been his
father really wasn't a threat to them
after the 73 war and so they like things
just the way they are now if Isis takes
over control of Syria all bets are off
and I think the Israelis would probably
be wise to assume that Isis would attack
them soon after taking power and that's
why the Israelis haven't played a role
in this whole thing
because they don't want to be drawn in
they don't want to
turn um otherwise neutral players
against them and for Isis by really
taking a public stand they just quietly
support ass
said all right well it seems as though
with what NATO has been doing and
encroaching further east into Russia
that this has a lot of similarities of
what's going on between this almost and
I don't want to say it's a proxy war
between the US and Russia in Syria but
it is it is uh has a lot of similarities
to that and um we now have S uh Russia
saying that they have not taken nuclear
weapons off the table as a threat to
Isis they're now ramping up the type of
military uh operations that they're
doing and none of what they're doing is
going after
Isis they're going after some
asymmetrical uh tactics or strategies
towards either turkey NATO or the United
States yeah this is a brilliant
opportunity for the Russians to test out
their new equipment and to give their
pilots um real life training in in air
battles this is something that the
Russians have been looking forward to
for for many many years and frankly it's
something that we do all the time I mean
when when we launch these you know no
fly zones or um bombing runs these are
these are really training exercises
using live weapons and and this is how
we ensure that our Pilots are the best
in the world well the Russians have been
left out of that over the last few
decades and now this is their turn to
train their pilots and to test their
weapons wow okay to shift gears so I can
let you go in a recent interview with
Jared Leto that I'm going to post and
I'm going to post other things that
you've done and I've got up here on the
screen how people could support you um
through through your different funding
because you have uh uh John's given up
um so much for the United States in
order to let us know about how things
are really working he doesn't want to be
considered the torture guy anymore and
then it what's really important about
what John has said recently is that
we're losing our civil liberties that
the CIA since 2001 has been lying to us
as his exact words and he wants to get
this information out so John what could
you say to people who are listening
about how critically important it is for
us to stand up and speak out to protect
our civil liberties and how would they
do
that I I'm very pained that most
Americans seem to have been willing
since the passage of the Patriot Act in
October of 201 2001 to just give up many
of the civil liberties that they've
enjoyed really since the since the ation
of the country uh without so much as a
debate we're not seeing demonstrations
in the streets we're not seeing rallies
on Capitol Hill and in fact it seems
like every time the government wants to
pass uh legislation it it includes um
something that strips us of some of our
our personal freedoms this is something
that Americans really have to oppose now
whether it has to do with with torture
or with privacy privacy is a very
important issue right now especially as
it relates to to cyber privacy we need
to ride our elected officials and we
need to force them to understand that we
are not willing to give up these rights
without a fight we should tell them that
the Patriot Act is unconstitutional it
needs to be changed and that Americans
have an inherent right to privacy it's
something that we haven't done yet and
it's very important to me so the way
they do it sometimes is nibbling around
edges and the most recent one is
encryption explain what how they're
going uh how they're using encryption
now to take away our personal freedoms
right you know encryption is such an
important issue that I think most
Americans don't understand um I've got
my iPhone right here and on my iPhone
I've got um uh some encrypted apps I
have something called signal I have
another app called redphone that allows
me to make an encrypted phone call I
have another thing called WhatsApp
that's uh that's encrypted and it's
encrypted because I don't want the
government intercepting my
communications the government has no
right to intercept my communications
without a warrant we have
constitutional uh guarantees um of of uh
due process and so without a warrant the
government has no right to know what I'm
saying in my emails or my text messages
or my telephone calls now the
government most particularly uh FBI
director Comey argues that encrypted
applications are what the terrorists are
using to communicate first of all that
is just simply not true if you look at
the communications between the Paris
attackers they used online gaming
systems to communicate that was that
those gaming systems were not encrypted
uh they were out there in The Ether for
anybody to intercept and in fact NSA CIA
and FBI did not intercept those
Communications I call that an
intelligence failure not a problem with
encryption now even in in San Bernardino
they're talking about encryption having
been used I would counter that just
decent police work would have disrupted
that attack the FBI knew that Sayed
Farooq was in contact with a known
terrorist overseas yet they did nothing
about it they never questioned him they
never detained him they never sought a
warant to to go into his home or into
his electronics they just let him go
that was bad police work so it's not
that encryption is preventing the FBI
from doing its job it's that the FBI is
bad at doing its job that's not the
American people's fault and that's not a
reason to ban encryption so what are the
two or three things that Americans
should be contacting the representatives
about well number one I think we should
be we should be like I said riding our
elected officials to ensure that that
personal encryption remains legal
another thing um that we should be
talking to our elected officials about
is is the repeal of the Patriot Act um
you know NSA AR has in its Charter that
it is forbidden from from spying on
American citizens in fact now much of
what uh NSA does is to spy on American
citizens so we need hard and fast laws
that protect us from the long arm of the
NSA and we have no such law and the
third thing is you know we've never
really settled on the on the torture
issue uh we need to make sure that
torture never rears its ugly head again
well the president the day before
Christmas signed the National Defense
authorization act which was I think
unprecedented 2-year budget appro
approval to uh uh which I can't
understand how they were allowed to do
that but he vetoed it originally weeks
earlier because he wanted to have
Guantanamo um closed yes and now he's
not going to do that and there's almost
a hundred people who are uh have been
imprisoned for 13 14 years uh without
due process and they just released
someone who had been arrested uh who had
been in there for 13 years who they had
the wrong identity on yes um would that
be a fourth issue that you think and how
would the president through executive
orders uh release the rem or uh U Move
the remaining hundred prisoners and
why I've not un I've not understood the
the cowardice of the Republican party on
this issue it seems like every
Republican senator and every Republican
Congressman has this irrational fear of
a
terrorist um serving his time in a
prison in these congressman's districts
or Senator States as though we don't
have dangerous people in our maximum
security prisons right now if we're
going to be Americans in the spirit of
America and showing respect to the
Constitution we will take the prisoners
that we have at
Guantanamo we will charge those who have
committed a crime with a crime we will
give them their day in court and if
they're found guilty we would
incarcerate them in an American prison
if we're not going to do that they
should be
released they've not been charged with a
crime they've not been found guilty of a
crime they've not been able to face
their accusers in court to me that means
they're not guilty of anything and they
should be released I regret that the
president has not had the guts to close
Guantanamo in the seven plus years that
he's been president for seven years that
he's been
president um with that said the
Republicans are at least as guilty as
the President is on this issue so yeah
Guantanamo is the fourth thing that we
need to we need to Force action on
unfortunately though I think the
American people seem to prefer the
status
quote well I'm honored to have the
opportunity to talk to you in detail
about what's going on all of these
issues lead up to uh breeding more
terrorism uh spending taxpayers dollars
more ridiculously instead using them
domestically for things that we need
here it's killing innocent people John
is one of the few people who stood up
for to in order to protect all this so
I'd really like you to support him his
book is The Reluctant spy I'll have
links to other things John you're an
amazing person thank you you're a great
guy AR thanks a lot for doing this all
right take care my pleasure bye
byee